Finding Aid for Helen Jackson Claytor papers, 1924-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Helen Jackson Claytor papers 1924-2005, 1955-1985
Claytor, Helen Jackson.
1 oversize folders
1 oversize volumes
6 linear feet
8763 Aa 2; Ac
Grand Rapids, Michigan, clubwoman, officer in the Grand Rapids chapter of the Young Women's Christian Association, president of the national YWCA, 1967-1973. Primarily speeches delivered on topics relating to the YWCA, civil rights, citizenship, and the family; speeches reflect in part her thoughts as a black woman on questions of school and housing segregation; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Helen Jackson Claytor (donor no. 7193 ) and came to the library in 1984. A second acquisition was received on June 29, 2006, and came from her daughter Judith Claytor.
The collection is open to research.
Helen Jackson Claytor was born April 12, 1907 in Minneapolis, Minnesota. It was here that she began her lifelong association with the Young Women's Christian Association as a member of the girl reserves. She graduated from the University of- Minnesota with an education degree in 1928.
Unable to find a teaching job, Claytor took a position with the YWCA in Trenton, New Jersey for two years and then moved to a similar position in Kansas City. There she married Earl Wilkins, a journalist and the brother of NAACP director Roy Wilkins. Claytor gave up her job until her husband became seriously ill, at which time she began to work for a black YWCA chapter in Kansas City. Following Earl Wilkins' death, Claytor accepted a position with the national YWCA as secretary for Interracial Education. In 1943, she married Dr. Robert Claytor of Grand Rapids, Michigan. After completing a study of race relations for the YWCA national board, Mrs. Claytor resigned her staff position but remained active in local and national YWCA affairs.
In 1949, Claytor was elected president of the Grand Rapids, YWCA. She was the first black woman to head an integrated YWCA chapter. She served on the national board of the YWCA, 1946-1973, and was also a member of the YWCA World Council, 1946-1952 and 1967-1972. Mrs. Claytor was elected to two terms as president of the national YWCA, 1967-1973.
Helen Claytor died May 10, 2005.
The Helen J. Claytor papers primarily document her leadership in both the National and Grand Rapids YWCA, her community work on a local and national level, as well as the speeches she delivered, ca. 1940-1985, on topics relating to her activities in the YWCA, the civil rights movement, and the Episcopal Church.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Civil rights--United States.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Race relations.; Women--Michigan--Grand Rapids--Societies and clubs.; Young Women's Christian Associations.; African American women--Michigan.; Young Women's Christian Association (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Claytor, Helen Jackson.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Women.; Claytor, Helen Jackson.; Lebanon.; Women.; Young Women's Christian Associations.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical/ Personal 1924-2005
  The first series, Biographical/Personal (approx. 1 linear feet) spans the dates 1924-2005, and includes various awards and their corresponding acceptance speeches, date books and calendars, biographical sketches and resumes, and several folders of magazine articles by or about Mrs. Claytor. Of particular note is a scrapbook chronicling her life from 1924 to 1988.
  - Date Books and Calendars 1950-1980s, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Sketches/Resumes undated, 1963, 1965, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Funeral/ Memorial Service 2005 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Cards and Letters undated, 1946, 1960-2003, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - White House Invitations 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Awards 1967-1985
    - Michigan State Medical Society Award 1971 (Box 1)
      (photographs)
    - Beahan Award 1993 (Box 1)
    - "E" Quality Award 2000 (Box 1)
    - The Mayor's All-America City Award January 1, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Women Hall of Fame 1985, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Michigan Youth Commission, certificates of appointment (Folder 1)
      (located at Ac)
    - Helen Claytor Day 1973
      - Correspondence (Box 1)
      - Album (Box 1)
    - Helen J. Claytor Merit of Distinction Award 1983 (Box 1)
    - Junior Achievement Award (includes photographs), May 16, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Various Awards and Distinctions 1948, 1955, 1967-2002, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Magazine and Newspaper Articles (by and about Helen Claytor)
    - Various Articles (by and about) undated, 1941-1977, 1990, 1993-2002, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (see also oversize folder)
    - Religious Faith Series in Grand Rapids Press 1955 (Box 1)
    - Flair Section of the Grand Rapids Press, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Scrapbook circa 1924-1988 (scattered dates) (Volume 1)
  - Degrees 1928-1985
    - Aquinas College (Doctor of Humanities Honorary Degree) 1985 (Box 2)
    - Eastern Michigan (Doctor of Humanities Honorary Degree) 1968 (Box 2)
      (includes photographs)
    - University of Minnesota 1928, 1967-1968 (Box 2)
    - Western Michigan University (Doctor of Public Service Honorary Degree) 1972 (Box 2)
- Young Women Christian Association (YWCA) 1939-1990
  The second series, Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA) (approx. 1.5 linear feet) spans the dates 1939-1990 and contains materials related to Helen Claytor's leadership activities in the YWCA. It is divided into three subseries: General, Grand Rapids Branch, and National Branch. General includes various newspaper clippings related to Helen Claytor's career from 1940 to 1990, her personal notes on religion and worship, as well as several professional photographs. Grand Rapids Branch, 1949-1985, includes committee materials, early Board of Director documents, and correspondence. National Branch, 1939-1989, includes general administrative materials, correspondence, as well as large topical file covering civil rights, housing, race relations, women, and youth. Of particular note is Helen Claytor's 1944 groundbreaking manuscript, "Interracial Practice in Community YWCA's."
  - General 1940-1990
    - Newspaper Clippings 1940s-1990s, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Notes 1940-1985
      - Religion and Worship 1950-1968 (Box 2)
      - YWCA Conventions 1940-1965, 1968-1985, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous Press and Publications 1955-1980 (Box 2)
    - Presidential Nomination Materials 1967 (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Professional) 1964-1985 (Box 2)
  - Grand Rapids Branch 1949-1985
    - Annual Meeting Materials 1957, 1968-1980 (Box 2)
    - Association Review 1954, 1970, 1976, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Board of Directors 1949, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Capital Fund Campaign Committee 1980-1985 (Box 2)
    - Constitution and By-laws 1960, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1950-1967, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Council of Michigan YWCA's undated (Box 2)
    - Michigan Youth Commission's "Open-Ended" Conference 1967 (Box 2)
    - Programs 1950-1951, 1968, 1979 (Box 2)
  - National Branch 1939-1989
    - General 1949-1989
      - Bureau of Communications 1949, 1953-1971 (Box 3)
      - Constitution and By-laws circa 1970s, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1950-1967, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
      - Financial Materials 1960 (Box 3)
      - Programs 1964, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Topical Files 1939-1988
      - Civil Rights 1949, 1959, 1963 (Box 3)
      - Commission to Study the YWCA as a Christian Movement
        - undated 1960-1964 (Box 3)
        - 1965, 3 folders (Box 3)
        - 1966 (Box 3)
        - Reports and Printed Works undated, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
      - Housing: "Open Doors: A YWCA Guide for Open Housing," 1960 (Box 3)
      - Institute for Leadership in Intergroup Relations 1960, 1969
        - Leadership Kit February 1-5, 1960 (Box 3)
        - Notes and Correspondence undated, 1960, 1969 (Box 3)
      - Race Relations undated, 1939-1971
        - Correspondence undated, 1955-1971 (Box 3)
        - Notes 1939, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Institutional Racism (One Imperative: Eliminate Racism)
          - Action Audit for Change 1970-1971 (Box 3)
          - "Interracial Practices in Community YWCA's" 1944 (Box 3)
          - Miscellaneous Printed Works undated, 1970 (Box 3)
          - National Racial Justice Institute 1969 (Box 4)
      - Women, Correspondence and Notes undated, 1952-1968, 1988 (Box 4)
      - Youth 1967
        - Press Conference of Youth Opportunity 1967 (Box 4)
        - Summer Youth Demonstration Project 1967 (Box 4)
- Grand Rapids Community Work 1952-1983
  The third series, Grand Rapids Community Work (approx. 1.5 linear feet) spans the dates 1952-1983, and contains materials related to Helen Claytor's community relations activities in Grand Rapid. The Grand Rapids materials, 1952-1983, are organized by topic covering education, housing, urban renewal, and busing, and includes committee materials, correspondence, personal notes, newspapers clippings, reports, and essays.
  - Education 1953-1981
    - Board of Education 1955-1981
      - Citizen's Committee Minutes 1965-1966 (Box 4)
      - Committee for Better Education 1955, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - Calendars and Notes 1961-1970, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Committee on Compulsory Education undated, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Desegregation 1954-1966
      - Correspondence 1954, 1966 (Box 4)
      - Newspaper Clippings 1966 (Box 4)
    - Racial Imbalance Committee 1953-1968
      - Maps and Statistics 1965-1968 (Box 4)
      - Newspaper Clippings 1966 (Box 4)
      - Reports and Supplemental Writing 1953-1966, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Housing: Human Relations Commission (Housing Committee) 1952-1965
    - Correspondence and Notes 1963 (Box 4)
    - Incorporation Materials and Policies 1963 (Box 4)
    - Minutes 1959-1965 (Box 4)
    - Press Materials, undated 1955, 1965 (Box 4)
    - Reports (submitted by other organizations) undated, 1952-1957, 1960-1962, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Short Essay Analysis (submitted by other organizations) 1956-1963 (Box 4)
    - State Advisory Committee 1956 (Box 4)
  - Urban Renewal 1960-1963
    - Urban Renewal Advisory Committee (State of Michigan) 1962 (Box 5)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1960, 1961, 1967 (Box 5)
    - Workable Programs 1957, 1960-1963, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Other Topics 1970-1983
    - Busing 1970-1973
      - Essays 1970-1973 (Box 5)
      - Newspaper Clippings 1972-1973 (Box 5)
    - Church Women United 1993 (Box 5)
    - Creston Neighborhood Association 1981-1982
      - Awards and Notes 1981 (Box 5)
      - Board of Directors 1981 (Box 5)
      - Newsletters 1981-1982 (Box 5)
    - Community Relations Commission, Commemorative Anniversary Celebration 1983 (Box 5)
    - Hospice of Grand Rapids 1981-1983
      - Board of Directors 1981-1983 (Box 5)
      - Nominating Committee 1981-1982 (Box 5)
- National Conferences / Committees 1960-1971
  The fourth series, National Conferences / Committees (0.5 linear feet) spans the dates 1960-1971 and primarily documents Helen Claytor's participation in the White House conference called "To Fulfill These Rights," and include agendas, memorabilia, correspondence, newspaper clippings, reports, and photographs.
  - Conference on Children and Youth 1960 (Box 5)
  - To Fulfill These Rights (White House Conference) 1965-1966
    - Agendas and Participants 1965-1966 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1965-1966 (Box 5)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1966 (Box 5)
    - Notes and Memorabilia 1966 (Box 5)
    - Programs and Booklets 1966 (Box 5)
    - Reports 1965-1966 (Box 5)
  - Women's Advisory Committee for the Office of Economic Opportunity 1971 (Box 5)
- Speeches undated, 1940-1985
  The last series, Speeches (approx. 1.5 linear feet), spans the dates 1940-1985. This series has been arranged in two broad categories based on the audience to which they were given. The first group includes speeches Mrs. Claytor delivered to various YWCA groups in her capacity as a YWCA staff member or officer. The speeches cover a range of topics including, the interracial practices and policies of the YWCA, the YWCA as a vehicle for social change, the YWCA position on post-World War II nationalist movements, the importance of volunteer service organizations, and the role of women and women's organizations in the United States. The second category of speeches reflects some similar themes, but was delivered to non-YWCA audiences. There are a number of speeches, ca. 1940-1981, on civil rights and racial equality in general, and several addressing the questions of school and housing segregation in Grand Rapids. Other topics include citizenship, women's organizations, the family, and religious worship.
  The speeches have been foldered by individual speech title or by speech subject. Mrs. Claytor often used several versions of a speech and frequently incorporated parts of one speech into another. As a result, a text may contain several pagination sequences. An attempt has been made to reconstruct the original speech and file with it speeches that incorporated part of the original text. In some cases, the more significant speeches in a subject file have been individually cited in the contents list.
  - YWCA Groups
    - undated, 1940s
      - "One World Under God" (Box 5)
      - "New Trends in the YWCA" (Box 5)
      - "The YWCA and the Good Life" (Box 5)
      - "External Tensions in the Community and World" (Box 5)
      - "From Faith to Action in the YWCA" (Box 5)
      - "Building a Responsible Unity" (Box 5)
      - "Reaching Individual Security Through World Cooperation" (Box 5)
      - "World Citizenship" (Box 5)
    - 1941-1949
      - "Relation of the YWCA to National Defense," 1941 (Box 5)
      - "YWCA as a Movement," 1941 (Box 5)
      - "YWCA and World Fellowship," 1944, 1952 (Box 5)
      - "The YWCA and the Coming World Order," circa 1945 (Box 5)
      - Reports on YWCA World Council Meeting, Hangchow, China 1947 (Box 5)
      - YWCA World Council Committee on Status of Women 1948 (Box 5)
      - "The YWCA: An Institution and a Social Force," 1948, 1953 (Box 5)
      - "Grand Rapids YWCA President's Report 1949, 1950 (Box 5)
      - "Women of Valor," 1949, 1953 (Box 5)
    - 1951-1959
      - Reports on YWCA World Council Meeting, Beirut 1951-1952 (Box 5)
      - "Through the Barriers of Nationalism," 1951 (Box 5)
      - "The YWCA Does a Vital Job," 1952 (Box 5)
      - "YWCA and the Refugee Problem," 1952 (Box 5)
      - Speeches on Mid East Tour 1953 (includes photographs) (Box 5)
      - YWCA Centennial Speeches 1953-1954 (Box 5)
      - Speeches on "Y Teens," 1954-1955 (Box 5)
      - YWCA Public Affairs Program 1955 (Box 5)
      - Workshop on Cooperation 1956 (Box 5)
      - "Balancing," 1957-1959 (Box 5)
    - 1960-1970
      - "The Value of Committed Volunteers to the YWCA," 1960 (Box 5)
        includes other notes on voluntarism
      - Role of YWCA in the 1960s (Box 5)
      - "National Interest in Intergroup Relations," 1960 (Box 5)
      - "Looking in to the 1960s" 1961 (Box 5)
      - "Winds of Change," 1962 (Box 5)
      - "New Dimensions and New Demands," 1962 (Box 5)
      - "Youth Work Comes Alive," 1962 (Box 5)
      - "Where You Can Belong," 1962 (Box 5)
      - YWCA Leadership Workshop 1962 (Box 5)
      - "The Meaning of Belonging to the YWCA," 1963, 1964, 1966 (Box 5)
      - "She Would Rather Light a Candle," 1964 (Box 5)
      - Speech to World Fellowship Meeting, Detroit 1966 (Box 5)
      - "The YWCA as a Christian Movement," 1966, 1967 (Box 6)
      - Speeches for YWCA Chapter Anniversaries 1966-1970 (Box 6)
      - Minneapolis, 75th Anniversary 1966 (Box 6)
      - Cleveland, 100th Anniversary 1968 (Box 6)
      - Greenwich, 50th Anniversary 1968 (Box 6)
      - Mt. Vernon, 50th Anniversary 1968 (Box 6)
      - Los Angeles, 75th Anniversary 1969 (Box 6)
      - Germantown, 100th Anniversary 1970 (Box 6)
      - Workshop Speeches 1967-1968 (Box 6)
      - YWCA National Convention 1967 (Box 6)
      - Speeches at National Board Meetings 1968-1970 (Box 6)
      - "Black Leadership in the YWCA," 1969 (Box 6)
      - Speeches to Regional YWCA Meetings 1969 (Box 6)
      - "Unity in a Shared Struggle," 1970 (Box 6)
    - 1971-1985
      - YWCA World Council Meeting 1971 (Box 6)
      - Speeches at YWCA Chapter Meetings 1972-1979 (Box 6)
      - "The 'Y' and I," 1974 (Box 6)
      - "The 'W' Makes a Difference," 1975 (Box 6)
      - Speech to Detroit World Service Council 1977 (Box 6)
      - "Membership: A Survival Issue for the YWCA 1977 (Box 6)
      - "New Trends in Voluntarism," 1978 (Box 6)
  - Non-YWCA Groups undated, 1940-1981
    - Race Relations undated, 1940-1981
      - Undated, circa 1940-1949 (Box 6)
      - 1950-1959 (Box 6)
      - 1960-1981 (Box 6)
    - School Desegregation in Grand Rapids 1954 (Box 6)
    - Housing Segregation in Grand Rapids 1950s (Box 6)
    - Grand Rapids Human Relations Commission 1952-1962 (Box 6)
    - Human Relations Speeches 1953-1969 (Box 6)
    - National Steering Committee for Civil Rights 1963 (Box 6)
    - Speech to National Association of Social Workers 1965 (Box 6)
    - Role of Women's Organizations undated, 1944, 1962 (Box 6)
    - Speeches to Women's Organizations 1959-1969 (Box 6)
    - "Mother Speech," 1949, 1968, 1971, 1981 (Box 6)
    - Freedom Agenda Forum 1956 (Box 6)
    - Freedom and Responsibility 1968 (Box 6)
    - Worship Speeches 1955-1969 (Box 6)
    - Speeches to Church Groups 1955-1978 (Box 6)
    - White House Conference on Children 1960 (Box 6)
    - Testimonials and Introductions by Helen Claytor 1967-1968 (Box 6)
    - Book Reviews circa 1964, 1978 (Box 6)